<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heauenly meditations vpon the publicans prayer</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849886</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15058</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15058)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 789:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heauenly meditations vpon the publicans prayer</title>
                  <author>T. F., fl. 1606.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35, [6] leaves : 16#20.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. R[oberts] for Iohn Flasket,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.F.</note>
                  <note>The dedication by T.F. indicates he is not the author--STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15058:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15058:1"/>
            <p>HEAVENLY Meditations VPON THE PVB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans Prayer:</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 18. 13.</bibl> O God, be mercifull to mee a Sinner.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by I. R. for Iohn Flasket. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15058:2"/>
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of Henry Wallop and Elizabeth, daughter of Richard Corbet of Morton-Corbet</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:15058:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, my worthy and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Patron, Sir <hi>Henry Wallop, Knight, high Sherieffe of Shrop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiere,</hi> and to the vertuous Lady Elizabeth his wife.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AS Christian modestie, (right Worſhipfull) moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a Deuine (I make no question) the Authour hereof, not onely to conceale his Name, but alſo to ceaſe from ſetting foorth any thing in the praiſe of that, which of right deſerueth to be commended: So Christian iustice and equitie, which wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to giue to euery thing his due, would not ſuffer mee to let that paſſe without ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, where-vnto I am not able ſufficiently to giue any.
<pb facs="tcp:15058:3"/> But conſidering, that ſlightly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend a thing, were the next way to diſpraiſe it, except with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all it were ſhrowded vnder the patronage of ſome worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and thinking it vnmeete to let that goe like an Orphant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, which had a Father at home, I preſumed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Worſhips patronages, not a bare Lawrell, which of it ſelfe for the greeneneſſe (when other be withered) may ſeeme to be accepted, but the ſame decked &amp; adorned with most Heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Meditations: So that as I think, if your Worſhips were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with a materiall Lawrel, (wherin beſides naturall green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, were but this neceſſarie
<pb facs="tcp:15058:3"/> vſe, that it could defend you in your Garden from the heate of the Sunne) you would accept, if not of the gift, yet the good-will of the giuer: So relying my ſelfe vpon your accuſtomed fauour &amp; clemencie, I hope you will afford ſome fauourable acceptation heereof: for heerein is not that greenenes, which conſisting of naturall qualities, must then wither whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all things haue their ending, according to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the flouriſhing greene promiſes of the couenaunt of God, which (as GOD himſelfe) last alwaies immutable, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable. Heere are not the beautifull leaues of a materiall tree, which delight onely the
<pb facs="tcp:15058:4"/> outward ſight, but a moſt fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar view of GOD himſelfe in Chriſt, euen to the delight of the ſoule, and the inward comfort of the ſpirit, which take pleaſure onely in heauenly thinges. To conclude, heere you are not ſhrowded from the heate of the Sunne, but ſhall finde moſt coole ſhade from the parching heate of ſinne: from which, as in dutie I am bound, I will pray that God in this life ſhielde &amp; defend you both, and in the life to come, graunt you euerlasting rest.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt bounden and dutifull Orator. T. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15058:4"/>
            <head>HEAVENLY <hi>Meditations.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>O God be mercifull to mee a Sinner.</q>
            <p>CHriſt our precurſor into Heauen, euen to his laſt breath not vnmindful of his little-little flock, did as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham<note place="margin">Gene, 25, 1, Reg, 2,</note> vnto Iſaack, as Dauid vnto Salomon, as Tobias vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Tob, 4.</note> his ſonne, bequeath vnto them, a few ſmall howres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his glorification, his beſt &amp; principall legacie, Eternall life; confirming it vnto them in his laſt and lateſt prayer, made for his Apoſtles; This is life eternall, that they know<note place="margin">Iohn, 17,</note> thee to be the only very God,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:5"/> and whom thou haſt ſent Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. That wee know<note place="margin">Rom, 11,</note> him, <hi>quis et qualis est,</hi> who he is, and what he is? who he is, <hi>à quo, in quo, per quem ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi> The principall and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler eſſence, from whom, by whom, &amp; in whom all things were created, all thinges are preſerued, all thinges ſhall be reſolued; what hee is, to wit,<note place="margin">Zanch. li. 3. de Nat. Dei. que. ſtio. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Sapientiſsimus, qui ſciat; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſsimus, qui poſsit; aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimus, qui velit ſuos ſeruare.</hi> Great in wiſedom, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore knoweth, powerfull in ſtrength, and therefore can, plentifull in loue, and therfore wil crowne thoſe with eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which he knoweth; know
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15058:5"/> thoſe euerlaſtingly, which he loueth; loue thoſe moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, which knowe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him. By his know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge hee will rule, by his ſtrength defend, by his loue, loue all, that knowe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him; that knowe him after a long and earneſt ſeeking him, &amp; acknowledge him, by a moſt gracious and happy finding him; ſeeking him among their miſeries, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him in his mercies; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him in the crowde and preſſe of theyr ſinnes, finding him in the top of his Croſſe, in the large promiſes of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Seeking him in finding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, finding him in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:15058:6"/> themſelues.</p>
            <p>For as wee deſire to finde God, ſo we muſt endeuour to ſeeke our ſelues; ſo true it is there muſt be <hi>cognitio nostri,</hi> before there can bee <hi>agnitio Dei;</hi> a queſt, and inquiſition made about our ſelues, before wee can reach the knowledge of him that made vs; for God being as he is <hi>ſummum genus,</hi> not vſed to definition, not ſubiect to deſcription, muſt be ſhadowed <hi>per posteriora,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath not <hi>priora,</hi> hee beeing <hi>primum principium,</hi> the primarie cauſe, and principall ground of euery principle, yea that <hi>principiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principorum,</hi> that illimmited, wonderfull, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15058:6"/> vnſearchable Alpha, muſt bee<note place="margin">Apoc, 1.</note> comprehended and knowne to his effects, <hi>principiorum non est querenda Ratio,</hi> It is meere dotage in Philoſophie to ſearch out cauſes of principles when as they are principles. They haue not precedent cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; therefore Boetius giues this cannon, <hi>Sires á prioribus per cauſas demonſtrari non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, á posteribus per effect a ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicari debent,</hi> thoſe thinges that borrow not theyr proofe and demonſtration, from fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>running cauſes, their bearing and luſter, muſt bee deriued from their effects.</p>
            <p>Since then God in regard of beginning is incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:7"/> and voyd of all demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration <hi>à priore,</hi> to declare his <hi>quid est,</hi> mans frailtie muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to knowe him <hi>á posterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> by his effects and workes. For <hi>inviſibilia Dei per ea quae fact a ſunt conſpiciuntur,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible wiſedome &amp; power of God, is ſeene by the creation of the world, and if any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the perfect arte of Gods omnipotencie, may bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, yet in nothing more then in man, vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſet the ſtampe of his owne Image. Man therefore muſt know him <hi>à posteriore,</hi> that is, firſt hee muſt knowe himſelfe, for man is his workmanſhip; then knowe God as hee is his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15058:7"/> Maker; firſt knowe himſelfe, with the eye of Experience, &amp; then know God with the eye of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation. Firſt know himſelfe, poore in miſery, and then know God, rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; firſt knowe himſelfe <hi>ſub iugo Mundi,</hi> groaning &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken vnder the yoke of ſin; and then know God, <hi>ſub iugo Chriſti,</hi> eaſing &amp; refreſhing the heauie laden ſin; Firſt knowe himſelfe, <hi>Mancipium mortis,</hi> Deaths free-hold and poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then know God, <hi>Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriam mortis,</hi> the bruſer and breaker of the Serpents head;<note place="margin">Gene, 3,</note> firſt knowe himſelfe, <hi>lucerna aduentum,</hi> the weake ſubiect of all mortality, &amp; then know
<pb facs="tcp:15058:8"/> God in the donation of his Spirit, the earneſt pennie of mans immortalitie.<note place="margin">2, Cor, 1,</note> He muſt knowe <hi>Quid est,</hi> that hee is a too-ſoone borne, and no long liuing creature, <hi>cum quibus eſt,</hi> that he is coupled with famin, with thirſt, with heate, with colde, with infirmitie, vvith death; <hi>cui ſimilis est,</hi> that he is like to ſnow, quick come, and quickly gone; like to a Roſe, at morning fayre, at euening withered. Hee muſt know, <hi>Vnde venit,</hi> from whence hee is, <hi>vbi eſt,</hi> where he is, <hi>quo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> whether hee will; whence he is, &amp; then bluſh for ſhame; where hee is, and then lament with groanes; whether he wil,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15058:8"/> and then tremble with feare: bluſh for ſhame at his naked natiuity; lament with grones at his worldly entertainment; tremble with feare at his dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end; bluſh for ſhame that he is become fleſh, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore farre from God; lament with groanes that hee is in the world, and therefore wide of heauen; tremble with feare, that he muſt die, and therfore obuious to the iawes of hell: to be briefe, hee muſt knowe himſelfe, <hi>intra et extra, á tergo et fronte, á dextris, á ſinistris, vndique,</hi> within and without, behind &amp; before, on this ſide, on that ſide, on euery ſide; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him his peruerſe &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart
<pb facs="tcp:15058:9"/> will, to that which is good; behind, his ſweet and pleaſing remembrance, to that which is bad; on this ſide lack of patience in aduerſitie, on that ſide, too much pride and haughtines in proſperitie; on euery ſide, <hi>vulnera á peccato inflicta,</hi> wounds, and nothing but wounds, imprinted and ſtamped into his ſoule &amp; fleſh by the cuſtome of ſinne. And then he ſhall find, God aboue him powerfull, beneath him plentifull, before him watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, behind him wonderfull, on this ſide bountifull, on that ſide carefull, on euery ſide mercifull. Mercifull in forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, mercifull in forgiuing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15058:9"/> ſinnes. That <hi>Manuſcript</hi> in the Temple of Delphos, <hi>Gnothi</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Coloten. Tom: 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſeamton,</hi> was ſo powerfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heathens, that the deepe learned Doctors dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Seipſos noſcere,</hi> the onely pathway to perfection: And therfore Heraclitus for ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition a Heathen, for profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion a philoſopher, on a time triumphing (as it were) with himſelfe, how he had ſpent the day, cryed out, <hi>Quaeſiui meip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plu. ibid.</note> the honour of the vvell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent day is this, I haue ſought my ſelfe. And Socrates vvas ſuch a pugill in the Caſtle of knowledge, ſuch a labourer in the arte of Seeking, that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotes the Epicure called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:15058:10"/> foole, becauſe he ſpent ſo much time in this one ſtudie, but <hi>non fuit Socrates ſiultus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>ſeipſum querens.</hi> Socrates ſaith Plutarch, did not deſerue the name of foole in this inquirie, and priuie ſearch of his owne infirmitie, <hi>cum ſit hoc cognitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neceſſarium inventus difficili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſeeing of all knowledge, this onely is moſt neceſſarie, and of learning the moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult. <hi>Difficile est, &amp;c.</hi> It is an harde thing, ſaith Chilo, to be tongue tyde in ſecrecie, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the time rightlie, to ſuffer<note place="margin">Diog. la: in vit. eius</note> iniuries patiently: &amp; <hi>difficile,</hi> it is a hard thing, ſaith Pittacus,<note place="margin">Id: in vit. eore.</note> to be a good man: &amp; as Bias, <hi>Difficile est,</hi> it is a hard thing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15058:10"/> to tollerate aduerſitie with quietnes.</p>
            <p>But if Thales <hi>Difficile</hi> may goe currant, <hi>Difficile est homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſeipſum noſcere,</hi> I may add, <hi>difficilimum est,</hi> The hardeſt leſſon that a man can learne, is to know himſelfe, <hi>Quid enim</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stella de cont: mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di: lib. 3. cap: 14.</note> 
               <hi>prodest ſcire artes liberales, ſic licet Doctor in omnibus niſi cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcas teipſum,</hi> what is the ſtile of maiſterſhip in Artes? what is the height of doctorſhip in faculties? Yet thy knowledge wants of her perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if thou want perfectly to knowe thy ſelf. <hi>Scientiainflat,</hi> knowledge puffeth vp, but ſelfe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge pulleth downe.<note place="margin">1, Cor, 8,</note> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is ſo farre wide of true
<pb facs="tcp:15058:11"/> knowledge, that in ignorance of GOD it cryeth with Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,<note place="margin">Exod. 5,</note> 
               <hi>Quis eſt Deus veſter?</hi> but ſelfe knowledge, plunged in the depth of his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, aſpireth to knowe the true knowledge of God, and<note place="margin">Exod, 18</note> with Iethro, confeſſeth <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus maior Dijs omnibus:</hi> the Lord is greater then all Gods: knowledge mounteth vppon the wings of pride, boaſteth<note place="margin">Eſay.</note> with Lucifer, <hi>aſcendam in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> I will make the ſtarres my foote-ſtoole, but ſelfe knowledge couered with the vaile of humility, falleth down<note place="margin">Iob, 1, 20</note> with Iob, and worſhippeth. Knowledge hippocriticallie deuoted, runnes a pace to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15058:11"/> Temple, and as the Phariſie, fills the Temple with a <hi>Non</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke, 18,</note> 
               <hi>ſunt ſicut alij,</hi> but ſelfe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, not haſtie in pace, not multiloquious in wordes, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping time in going, obſeruing a meane in ſpeaking, at one ſtroake vvith the Publican, breakes vppe the Cheſt of his hart, and <hi>Sub forma pauperis, ſub forma peccatoris,</hi> in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of a ſinner, craues; <hi>O God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All men, ſaith Ariſtotle, by<note place="margin">Metaph. Lib. 1.</note> nature couet knowledge, and that itching deſire of Eue, as ſoone as ſhee was out of the ſhell, teſtifieth no leſſe, when for the hope of <hi>Sciens bonum et malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> for the hope of much
<pb facs="tcp:15058:12"/> knowledge, ſhe loſt herſelfe in ignorance, ſwallowing as ſhee thought, the baite of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, vvhich turned in the end, the baine of ignorance. Yet if knowledge ſuffer a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and men beare more then an indifferent mind vnto it, there is none more pleaſing, none more profitable, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſelfe knowledge; pleaſing in reſpect of GOD, profitable in reſpect of man. It is that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomical Ladder of Iacob,<note place="margin">Gene, 28,</note> that reacheth from earth to heauen; from mans earth-bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried hart, to the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heauenly motions: that Geometrical ſquire, that ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth<note place="margin">Pſalm, 39</note> out man at a ſpan length,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15058:12"/> and then meaſureth God, the Alpha &amp; Omega, vvhich fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth heauen &amp; earth; that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmeticall kallender of mans age, that firſt declareth his time to be threeſcore yeeres &amp; tenne, and then with Moiſes aſcendeth the mount, to take a ſuruay of Gods Eternitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quo magis noueris teipſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stella de con: mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di: lib. 3, cap. 13.</note> 
               <hi>eo perfectius cognoſcere Deum,</hi> the deeper thou wadeſt into this ſelfe knowledge, the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer thou ſhalt ariue to GOD himſelfe. It ſhall be more then Thomas his <hi>Credo,</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue<note place="margin">Ioh, 20,</note> God inwardlie, then to thruſt thy finger into his ſide. It ſhall be more then the Centurions<note place="margin">Math, 27,</note> teſtimonie, <hi>Vera filius Dei erat
<pb facs="tcp:15058:13"/> hic,</hi> to acknowledge him in thy hart, then before the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe him with thy lippes. It ſhall be more then Simeons <hi>Nunc dimittis,</hi> to<note place="margin">Luke, 2,</note> take holde of him in troubled ſpirit, then to imbrace his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie in the fleſh. It ſhall be more then Phillips <hi>Sufficit,</hi> to<note place="margin">Ioh, 14,</note> view him in thy ſelfe, then to behold him in the heauens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nec te queſiueris extra,</hi> looke not on the ſuperficies &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of thy ſelfe, ſaith the Poet,<note place="margin">Perſius. Satyr. 1.</note> but rather let thy conſcience be thy looking glaſſe, wherby thou maiſt dreſſe &amp; attire thy ſelfe fit for heauen; that wil tel thee how to get <hi>vestem nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alem,</hi> the wedding robe, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15058:13"/> of life: that wil teach thee howe to put it on by a liuely ſaith; that will tell thee what thy progenitors haue been; that wil teach thee what thy ſtate is novv; that vvil tell thee hiſtories of Adam; that wil tel thee leſſons of thy ſelfe; that vvill tell thee Adam brought ſinne into the world; that vvill teach thee ſinne brought thee into the world; that vvill tell thee therefore thou muſt ſtudie lavve; that will teach thee therefore how thou maiſt ſtudie the law.</p>
            <p>Firſt thou muſt ſtudie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Per legem cognitio pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 3,</note> It is a Schoole-maiſter to bring vs vnto Chriſt; &amp; there
<pb facs="tcp:15058:14"/> like a true naturaliſt ſhalt thou finde, the cauſes of thy ſinne, hanging vpon Records, and like a true hiſtorian, there read what others haue done before thee. Secondly, hovve thou maiſt ſtudie Lawe, to vvit, by reading it vvith the gloſſe of the Goſpell, becauſe <hi>Per Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium cognitio gratiae,</hi> the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell is a true Interpreter of Saluation. Briefely, that vvill tel thee, how thou waſt borne vnder thoſe inceſtuous Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, Mars and Venus; that wil teach thee how thou muſt be borne againe vnder that Prince of Planets, the Sonne of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Deſcend therefore with <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodemus,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15058:14"/> from teaching the<note place="margin">Iohn, 3.</note> Lavv, to teach the true &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge of God; ſtriue with Marie, to bee bathed in the remiſſion of ſinnes, rather then to be drenched with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das in the Sea of deſperation; betake thy ſelf vnto God, that he may take thee vnto him.</p>
            <p>Thou art but man, therfore call vpon him thy God, thou art a ſinfull man, therfore pray vnto him thy mercifull God: It is no ſhame to be ſorowful, cry ô God; It is no reproch to begge mercies, pray him to be mercifull; It is no diſcredit to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe thy fault, tell him thou art a ſinner, and therefore em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened to ſay, <hi>O God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
<pb facs="tcp:15058:15"/> to me a Sinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the meanes which the ſinne-drowned Publican vſed in his extremitie of thirſt, to obtaine a refreſhing cup, with a beaten breaſt and broaken hart, to cry, <hi>O God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> If lamentable pictures, and wofull tales car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that force, to enforce teares from the hearers &amp; beholders eyes, then cannot we but turn prodigall in teares, vvhen vve behold this liuely counterfeit of ſorrow, where euery cullor hath a ſpeaking griefe, euery griefe a mourning tongue, to extort and wring teares from the beholders eyes. Iacob did<note place="margin">Gene, 27</note> neuer rent his garment in ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15058:15"/> many peeces for the loſſe of Ioſeph, as the Publican doth his ſoule for the burthen of his ſinne, laying it vpon the racke of repentance, and ſtretching it from earth to heauen; from himſelfe to God, till perforce he force it cry, <hi>O God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Agar beeing turned out of<note place="margin">Gene, 22</note> her Miſtris houſe, made her eyes the plaintifes of her ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie wandring; but the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, turning himſelfe out of his Maiſters fauour, makes his hand, hart, eyes, tongue and all, labour to chaſten his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe with true remorſe; His hands like the bellows, blowes the fire of Contrition to his hart, his heart like a limbecke
<pb facs="tcp:15058:16"/> diſtills the ſoueraine water of repentance into his eyes, like full ceſterns, not being able to looke vpward, returne theyr ſtreames backe vnto the hart, that ouer-charged, driues the floode of his affection to his tongue; His tongue like Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons Cenſor, conuaies the ſweete perfume of this preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſtillation, into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God himſelfe. And as the angels celebrated the birth of Chriſt with a ioyful himne, <hi>Gloria in excelſis Deo;</hi> ſo hee<note place="margin">Luke, 2,</note> welcoms his ſecond birth with this ſadde lamentation, <hi>O God be mercifull vnto mee a Sinner.</hi> Much like to Peter, when de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying<note place="margin">Math, 26</note> his Maiſters coate, <hi>fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15058:16"/> amare,</hi> hee made <hi>lachrimae</hi> the birth of his lamentation. Indeede ſicke men cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with melodie, as Saules frenſie could not endure Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids<note place="margin">1, Reg. 4,</note> Harpe; Salomons thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſongs, cannot mittigate the ſmart of the Publicans diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, that runnes altogether vpon the hart-ſtring, not the harpe ſtring; obſeruing thoſe <hi>Diaſemata acutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medeum, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue,</hi> the ſpaces, falls, and riſes of a melancholie dittie. The firſt note beeing raiſde high to him that is aboue all note, <hi>O God.</hi> The ſecond with a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſtoppe, mooued to a meane, <hi>be mercifull.</hi> The third with a heauie touch, fitted to
<pb facs="tcp:15058:17"/> the baſe, <hi>to mee a Sinner.</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, ô heauie is the note of man, and therefore it calls for moderation of God; Heauie, ô too heauie is the note of ſin, &amp; therefore it craues the voice of mercie, <hi>O God be mercifull, peccanti, to a ſinner, confitenti, to mee a Sinner; penitenti: O GOD be mercifull to me a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere I might iuſtly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in the Publican, firſt his invocation, <hi>O God,</hi> ſecondly, his petition, <hi>be mercifull,</hi> third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, his condition, <hi>to me a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> Yet ſuffer mee right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, leauing that doctrine to a ſecond ſuruay, at this time only to propoſe vnto you, the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15058:17"/> publican himſelfe in his medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, by vertue whereof hee attaineth to knowe himſelfe a Sinner, and God his Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Dauid being in the depth of meditation, <hi>concaluit cor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm, 39</note> his hart was hote, <hi>et exardeſcit ignis,</hi> the fire of his zeale vvas kinled, and hee ſpake, <hi>Lord teach mee;</hi> In the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts and ſtreites of meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the publican, <hi>concalet cor,</hi> his armes, like the Phaenix winges, hath ſet his heart on fire, <hi>et exardeſcit ignis,</hi> by that his zeale is inflamed; by his zeale his tongue is enlarged, and he ſpeakes; <hi>O God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</hi> He ſpeakes as Dauid, in meditation: that is, as <hi>Caſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15058:18"/> obſerueth, <hi>in conſilio, et</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſsiod. in eund. Pſal. Bias in Diog: La.</note> 
               <hi>deliberatione,</hi> with iudgement and diſcretion; he ſpeakes <hi>non cito,</hi> for that's <hi>inſaniae iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> either a point of madnes, or a fault of raſhneſſe; hee ſpeakes not <hi>cum loquacitate,</hi> for that is <hi>difficilimum, ſimul et multa, et oportune dicere,</hi> but he ſpeakes <hi>meditatio et oratione,</hi> his medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation teaching him what hee wants, his prayer directing to obtaine his wants. Laſtly, hee ſpeakes, and he ſpeakes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, by Platoes <hi>Licence,</hi> with<note place="margin">Plat. in Diog: La:</note> a prouiſo and reſpect, firſt, <hi>ad quem loquitur,</hi> to whom hee ſpeakes; ſecondly, <hi>quid loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> what it is hee ſpeakes; thirdly, <hi>qua multa loquitur,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15058:18"/> how much he ſpeakes; fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>quando loquitur,</hi> at what time hee ſpeakes. His firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, regards the reuerence of the perſon, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſpeakes, <hi>O God;</hi> his ſecond conſiſts of a two-folde proprietie, one drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe, <hi>a Sinner,</hi> the other by a neceſsitie from God, <hi>be mercifull;</hi> his third is couched, not ſo much in qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of words, as in quality of affection: For as <hi>Bucer</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,<note place="margin">Com: in 18. cap: Luc.</note> 
               <hi>orauit paucis, ſed affectu multo,</hi> his prayer is ſhort, but very ſweet; ſhort in reſpect of wordes, ſweete in regarde of zeale. His fourth and laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard aymes at the time, for ſinne, like Noahs flood, euery
<pb facs="tcp:15058:19"/> day getting ſtrength, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt come to the toppe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarat,<note place="margin">Gene, 7, 17.</note> and had almoſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpred the whole earth of man, ſo that it was high time to ſtay the ſwelling rage and furie of it; and therefore hee ſtriues to bring it backe to a lowe ebbe, with a ſmooth calme of an humble petition; and thus he ſpeakes in ſcrious meditation, <hi>O God be mercifull to mee a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> Helpleſſe man cannot helpe, therefore, <hi>O God,</hi> vvith whom is all comfort, <hi>be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull,</hi> which quickneſt the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit, therſore <hi>to me,</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing breath from Adam, and therefore <hi>a ſinner:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>O God be mercifull vnto
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15058:19"/> me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I runne not vnto the vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<note place="margin">Exod, 7.</note> with Pharaoh, I call not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any Idoll with the prieſts<note place="margin">1, Reg, 18</note> of Baall, but with ſorrowfull Sara in the gall of bitterneſſe,<note place="margin">Tob, 3.</note> with wrincle fac'd Iob, ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on the cheekes with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch,<note place="margin">Iob, 16</note> I beginne my confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>O God;</hi> I pray not for the ſtrength of body with Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;<note place="margin">Iudg, 16.</note> with Eliſha for my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies blindnes; with worldlie<note place="margin">2, Pet. 2.</note> Balaam for earthly treaſure; but with the faithfull Canani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh<note place="margin">Math, 15</note> woman, once and againe reiected, I begge for the crums of thy mercy, <hi>O God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:</hi> I, euen I, the ſonne of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, preſent my ſelfe vnto
<pb facs="tcp:15058:20"/> thee, &amp; as the Leaper entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his owne cleanſing, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen<note place="margin">Math, 8,</note> ſo I pray, <hi>O God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto me:</hi> I, euen I, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a long time fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the teates of thy loue, &amp; nouriſhed with the corrupt milke of ſinne, I, euen I, that haue refuſed thy heauenly Manna, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe with the leauen of Egipt, nowe at the length, ſtrooke with the-whip of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, retire, and for the eaſing of my griefe, preſume to ſollicite thee in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>O God be mercifull vnto me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I, am not of Simon Peters mind, that ſaid, Lord go from<note place="margin">Luke, 5,</note> mee, for I am a ſinfull man,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15058:20"/> but rather, Lord come to me, becauſe I am a ſinfull man; neither doe I cry out with the poſſeſſed; Ieſus thou ſonne of<note place="margin">Math, 8,</note> God, what haue I to do with thee? but rather, Ieſus thou ſonne of God, I haue to doe with thee. O let me haue ſom intereſt in thy loue, which like a vaile couereth the multitude of ſinnes, &amp; vniteth the peece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent hart of the ſorrow-beaten ſinner, <hi>O God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not with me, as it was<note place="margin">Gene, 4,</note> with Caine, to ſay my ſinne is greater then can be pardoned, neither am I as yet claſped in that deſperation and diſtruſt, as to equalize &amp; compare thy
<pb facs="tcp:15058:21"/> mercie to my ſinnes: I know thy pietie to exceed mans im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie, and thy mercie to be greater then mans miſerie: Sinnes as they cannot choke thy loue, ſo they cannot ſtand in any degree of compariſon with the <hi>infinitum</hi> of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie? For how much thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ouer-ſpreads mans weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo much the goodnes of thy goodneſſe, exceedes the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of his euill; and therefore, it were firſt high treaſon to thy Omnipotencie &amp; power, to ſay my ſinne is greater then thou canſt pardon, when as thy mercie is like thy ſelfe, great without all quantitie, good without all qualitie.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15058:21"/>
            <p>Secondly, it were a wrong vnpardonable to thy will, a treſpaſſe dangerous to thy truth, an iniurie too deſperate and deſpayring of thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to ſay thou wilt not doe what thou canſt, when with thee to doe, is as eaſie as to will, and to will is ready euery howre; wherefore, <hi>O God, be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is worſe then the ſtaine<note place="margin">Viex. in inſtit ad peniten.</note> of hippocriſie, to ſay I am no ſinner; for none can challenge to himſelfe that priuiledge, <hi>In mundo eſſe, non potest ſine cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa, qui in mundum venit cum culpa;</hi> ſinne was my Mother, which brought mee into the world, and ſinne is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:15058:22"/> of my affection in the vvorld.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Mundus non Mundus, quia</l>
               <l>Mundus polluit ergo,</l>
               <l>Qui manet in Mundo,</l>
               <l>quomodo Mundus erit.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="margin">Tho: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui: ca. 1. Epiſt. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi.</note>
            <p>The world is become a loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome cage of vncleane birds, a troubled ſea deuided into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny puddles, a dangerous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, nurſing ſtrange and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous creatures, where is <hi>Serpens flatu, adurens Scorpio, Cauda pungens, Dipſas latenter interficiens,</hi> where couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe like a burning Serpent, breathes out the fire of vnhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed deſires; where luſt like the Scorpion, venomes the ſoule, and prouokes it to black
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15058:22"/> atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts, where pride lies cloſe at the hart, like a ſnake lurking in the graſſe; where, nay where elſe, ſhould ſinne bee, when as <hi>Mundus</hi> is termed <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile omnium peccatorum,</hi> the denne and couert of all euill: where euery ſinne, great and little, though euery little ſinne be too great, raignes &amp; keepes his Court, <hi>Mundus non Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> the trimme faſhion of the world, is out of faſhion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſicke of euery faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it beeing compoſed <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile opus:</hi> the wonderful check and countermaund of all arte, is now become <hi>miſerabile cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os,</hi> the ruinous and diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red heape of all diſorder, <hi>mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus
<pb facs="tcp:15058:23"/> non mundus,</hi> it is the ſtage &amp; Theater of hipocriſie, faire and beautifull without, but ful of foule ſin within; like ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growing reedes, ſatisfying the eyes with a greene &amp; pleaſing out-ſide, but within nothing more vaine, nothing more light, nothing more emptie. Like Nabuchadnezars Idoll, glittering with a golden face yet ſtanding vppon feete of Clay. <hi>Mundus, non Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> by ſtriuing to excell in beautie, it hath waſht away all beautie, and there is no ſure hold for the foules anchor in ſo ſlipperie a ſtation: <hi>Mundus non mundus,</hi> the effects proue it ſo; for <hi>Mundus polluit,</hi> it is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15058:23"/> become Murthers ſlaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, Thefts refuge, Whore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doms ſtew, Oppreſsions ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and for all ſinnes a ſinfull Sanctuarie.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Ergo,</l>
               <l>Qui manet in Mundo,</l>
               <l>quomodo mundus erit.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Who then can ſwallow <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> cup &amp; not be transformed? who can taſt deadly poyſon &amp; ſcape infection? who can liue in Sodome &amp; not be wicked? who can breathe in the world and be no ſinner? Why? the Infant-bluſh at my natiuitie, was it not the Tell-tale of my originall ſinne, how I had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of that ſowre fruit, which all my anceſtors, <hi>á minore vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere, 6,</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:15058:24"/> 
               <hi>ad Maiorem, à propheta vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad Sacerdotem,</hi> from the firſt to the laſt had eaten: and from the time of my natiuitie, howe I haue ſince, hewen of my age by ſinne, filling, and fulfilling, as Chriſt ſaith, the meaſure of my Fathers, my ſinne-preſt conſcience ſecretly dooth tell mee; wherefore, <hi>O God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> There is no way to hide and ſmother what I am, for if diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed Adam, in his fig-leau'd coate, cloſe and ſecure as hee thought, among the buſhes could not ſhelter him from Gods preſence, howe can I promiſe to my ſelfe ſecuritie? well may the blindfold world,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15058:24"/> being as deeply couered in ſin as I, either for weakeneſſe not ſee, or for the thicke skinne of his owne ſinne, ſtill be dazell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed, &amp; not behold the heapes &amp; drifts of iniquitie; but God <hi>Qui vidit omnia generaliter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nicho: Denij ſe:</note> 
               <hi>ſine exceptione, euidenter ſine dubitatione, imutabiliter ſine obliuione,</hi> which hath intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of my ſecret thoughts, an eare to heare my priuate wordes, an eye to ſee my light and darke actions, God I ſay, which is a Scrutator of my hart and raines, hee enters the priuie chamber of my hart, &amp; is an eye witneſſe of my ſinne, before it be hatched, he knew all things before they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:25"/> and therefore he muſt needes know them when they are donne; <hi>Vidit te fornicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem cogitantem, antequam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit fornicantem,</hi> hee ſawe thee and Dauid intending adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, before thou and Dauid committed adulterie. If then no running away will ſerue the turn, no place cloſe inough to ſmother ſinne, when euerie thing is naked, and open to his view,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Cum quid turpe facis,</l>
               <l>cur me ſpectante rubeſcis,</l>
               <l>Curſpect ante Deo,</l>
               <l>non magis ipſe rubes.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Into what hard and obdurate mettall is man caſt, how is his face made ſtiffe, with the oylie
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15058:25"/> cullors of ſhameles impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that will feare the preſence of the creature, and no way ſtand in awe or reuerence, of the All-preſence of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor? Is there a ſecret roome where no man comes? a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſtage to act ſin where no man ſees; and is it poſsible to keepe God out? is it poſsible to blinde his eyes? <hi>Non te Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino abſcondis, ſed Dominum abſcondis tibi:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Viex in inſtit: ad poenit.</note> poore runne-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, thou hideſt not thy ſelfe from God, but rather hideſt GOD from thee. <hi>Eu videre ne quis,</hi> what though the eyes of thy vnderſtanding beeing darkned, thou canſt not ſee him, <hi>tamen ſubtilliter vidit
<pb facs="tcp:15058:26"/> omnia que agis,</hi> yet hath hee made a caſement to thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, &amp; beholds thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without, in the cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the action: wherfore, if running from God, be but a ſteppe to greater ſinne, then will I runne from ſin to God, and till I recouer ſtrength in him, will I not ceaſe to ſay, <hi>O God bee mercifull to mee a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſinne, as there is no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie to hide it, ſo there is no remedie to excuſe it, or to poſt it of with a <hi>Mulier que dedisti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene: 3.</note> the woman which thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt me did cauſe me to ſinne, as Adam did; or as Eue, to cleere herſelfe with a <hi>Serpens
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15058:26"/> decipit me,</hi> the Serpent begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mee; this is rather an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe then a decreaſe of ſinne, for <hi>culpa fit grauiora diſcuſſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Viex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitu:</note> 
               <hi>quam perpetrata,</hi> that offence was heauier in Examination, then it had beene before in Commiſsion; for <hi>Peccatum committunt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſum abſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt, negando abſconditum, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendendo adaugent:</hi> Heere the blind leade the blind, and the farther they goe, the greater is their danger; Firſt they ſinne, and then they flie: ſecondlie, they are taken, but they denie the Accuſation: thirdly, that beeing proued, they ſtand out in their owne defence, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the caſe with the Iudge,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:27"/> Adam excuſing him-ſelfe by the woman; the woman lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fault on the Serpent; both of them priuilie taxing GOD, for placing ſuch and ſuch with them in Paradice. But (alas) it is a naked ſhift, and to no purpoſe, to bandy words with God, neither did hee call them for any ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: For as the aboue no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted Authour noteth, <hi>Deus de peccato requiſiuit,</hi> GOD as it<note place="margin">Viex. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</note> were lamenting the firſt fruits of his labour, ſhould vtterlie perriſh, therefore queſtioned with our firſt Parents, <hi>Vt quod tranſgrediendo commiſerant, confitendo delerent:</hi> that the fire of their confeſsion might
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15058:27"/> burne downe the wall, which the rancor of ſinne had buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betweene them and God. As then hopefull Iſrael found meanes to ſupplant the vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Canauites, by electing<note place="margin">Iudg, 1.</note> Iuda their guide &amp; Captaine, ſo may I put to flight that great daring Cananite, that muſters vp whole legions of temptations againſt me, when as Iudah (which interpreted) ſignifies Confeſsion, doth not onely conduct and guide my forces, but alſo blunts the edge of my enemies ſword, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his intended poyſon to his owne confuſion.<note place="margin">Serm. 30, ad frat. in eremo.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obstruit os inferni Portas, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit Paradizi;</hi> The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſsion
<pb facs="tcp:15058:28"/> of thy ſinne, ſaith Auguſtine, barres vp the mouth of hell, which ſtandes gaping to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure thee, &amp; opens the gates of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that willingly would receiue thee. And againe ſaith the ſame Father, <hi>Appareat in confeſsione tua, macula cord is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm: 49 in Ioh. Euang.</note> 
               <hi>tui et pertinebis ad graege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti.</hi> Launch the feſtered ſoare with the knife of confeſsion, complaine to him that is the great Shepheard of ſoules, and as he is a Phiſitian, he wil cure thee, and as he is a Shepheard number thee with his flocke; <hi>Ingenue confeſsio meretur ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Viex: in inſtitu.</note> Sinnes ſaluing plaiſter, is to reueale it: for, <hi>Confiteri poſsum celare non voſſum,</hi> vvell
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15058:28"/> may I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe it, hide it I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; for ſo the deuil is preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his ſeuere accuſation, which his auncient malice would commence againſt vs: <hi>Si nostri accuſatores ſumus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n: de Rampela. tract: de con.</note> 
               <hi>proficit nobis ad ſalutem:</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomiſe &amp; exenterate ſinne, to poure it forth vpon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of repentance before God, wil not onely take away occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Plea from the Accuſer, but alſo reconcile the whole fauour of that high Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Niniuitae refitentur et vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vunt, Sodomitae obdurantur et pereunt:</hi> Belieuing Niniuie, wrapt and confounded in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, is turned from out her mourning gowne of Sacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth
<pb facs="tcp:15058:29"/> and aſhes, and girded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with a faire Syndon of Gods eternall fauor; but hard harted Sodome, ſwelling in the pride of her ſtrength, is ſtript of all her beautifull at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, &amp; nakedly left in the baſe aſhes of her own deſtruction. Therfore, <hi>confitebor aduerſum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> 
               <hi>me, iniusticiam meam Domino,</hi> I will confeſſe with Dauid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my ſelfe, my wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vnto the Lord, and ſay, <hi>O God be mercifull to me a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no vſurpation to turne Iudge, to call an aſsiſe, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my owne ſoule, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce my thoughts as accuſers, my conſcience as a thouſand
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15058:29"/> witneſſes, to auerre and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the guilt of ſin. Why, this ſhall preuent that latter &amp; fearefull examination howe I haue ſpent my time; howe I haue employed my wealth; howe I haue ruled my appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites; howe I haue mortified my deſires; howe I haue vſed and beſtowed all good gifts, and graces of the holy Spirit: Nay, I ſhall neuer haue cauſe to feare that dolefull <hi>Memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> which Abraham caſt in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues<note place="margin">Luke, 16</note> teeth, <hi>Fili recordare,</hi> ſonne reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, howe thou in thy life time receiuedſt pleaſure, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting thy time in wanton dalliance, ſolacing thy ſelfe in pleaſing paſtimes, braue in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:30"/> glittering in gold, high in honour, delicate in fare, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending pride to be but a point of Gentry; gluttony a part of good fellowſhip; wantonnes a tricke of youth; <hi>Nune ergo tu cruciaris,</hi> becauſe thou haſt incloſed, and taken in all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to thy ſelfe vppon Earth, thou ſhalt nowe take vp thy rents, &amp; reape a plentifull har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt in hell; <hi>Ante vltimum iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. 46. de tempore.</note> 
               <hi>Dei, tui compone cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam:</hi> Meete with the day of iudgement, ſaith Auſtine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it come; looke about be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand; thy ſelfe enter an action againſt thy ſelfe; For, <hi>non est vnde praeſumas, cum ille venerit,</hi> no preſumption will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15058:30"/> ſerue the turne: When hee comes, it will be too late to pleade ignorance; no boote to produce falſe witneſſe; no helpe to vſe colloured ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Ipſe erit Iudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſae tuae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. ead: Ser:</note> 
               <hi>qui modo est testis vestis tuae,</hi> hee ſhall then lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee, that in the act of ſin did onely apprehend thee, wherefore, to anoyde the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of that dreadfull day, to ſhunne the feare of that cry at mid-night, to preuent that ſentence, <hi>Goe ye curſed,</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that fauour, <hi>Come yee bleſſed,</hi> I heere accuſe my ſelfe of ſinne, &amp; with hope to find acceptance in the ſight of God, to him I reſort without
<pb facs="tcp:15058:31"/> delay, ſaying; <hi>O God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For indeede, delay as it is dangerous in it ſelfe, ſo it is mother to greater miſchiefes; though it ſeeme to old Iſaack, to our blind ſoule to haue the voice of Iacob, yet it is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of Rebeccaes deceit; by giuing too much audience to its ſugred ſpeeches, it ſteales a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our birth-right, &amp; throws vs quite out of the heritage of our Fathers; it giues ſinne the greater ſtrength; ſtrength of ſinne drawes on cuſtome; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome runnes into habite, and habite takes ſuch deepe roote, that it cannot, or will be verie hardly remoued. Hee that lets
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15058:31"/> his houſe runne to ruine, and will not at the firſt or ſecond breach ſeeke to reparrations, ſtriues to make rubbiſh of a good building. Hee that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells in a leaking ſhippe, and will not in the beginning looke to emptie it, ſayles for nought, but to drowne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. To morrow, to morrow, is the voyce of preſumption, for who can tell whether hee can liue till to morrowe? <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt: Serm: 30 ad fra: in eremo.</note> 
               <hi>Deus veniam penitenti, ſed non promiſit vſque in Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinum differenti,</hi> God ſayth Auguſtine, hath ſealed a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to him that repents, but none to him that deferres, and ſayes hee will repent. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:32"/> he that is not fit for his conuerſion to day, wil be leſſe readie to morrow, for</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Qui non est hodie,</l>
               <l>cras minus aptus erit.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="margin">Ouid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n re A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o.</note>
            <p>At the morrow hee will be the ſame man againe, and ſing the ſame ſong againe, languiſhing ſtill in delay, trifling out the time, till GOD (in whoſe hands onely are the moments of times) ſhut and barre him out from all time, and leaue him to paines without time, for ſo abuſing the precious date of time. To morrow, to morrow, is an vncertain time, and though the times be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in themſelues, yet are they moſt vncertaine vnto
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15058:32"/> man, who as he knew not his beginning, ſo hee is ignorant of his ending. Much like to little birds, that in their pearch looke about to flie this way, or that way, yet before they take theyr flight, they are preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſhaft. Death is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtate-ſearcher both of old and young, ſtriking as well Dauids young ſonne before it<note place="margin">2, Sam, 22</note> be ſeauen dayes olde, as that auncient of dayes of Methu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhelem, that liued nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixtie nine yeeres. Leaſt therefore the kingdome of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than ſhould bee eſtabliſhed in me, by frequentation of ſinne, I will breake off delay, putting no truſt in olde age, but as S.
<pb facs="tcp:15058:33"/> Paule ſaith, <hi>Dum cognomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hodie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb, 3,</note> euen in this verie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, while it is named to day, will I repentantly cry, <hi>O GOD be mercifull to mee a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moriantur ante te vitia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 12 ad Liuium.</note> giue thy ſinne (ſaith Seneca) leaue to die before thee: it is a good riddance of a painfull pardon, for it is little better then deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to free libertie to thy youthful wil to range abroad, vpon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence of repentance in thy laſt and leaſt part of thy life; For (alas) what can help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe old age help, when all the ſtrength of the body, all the faculties of the mind, all the parts &amp; paſsions, are not only
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15058:33"/> daunted, and out-dared with ſickneſſe, but alſo worne out with multitude of yeres: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as age-ſpent Dauid, is not able to retaine heate of himſelfe,<note place="margin">1, Reg, 1,</note> but Abiſhag the Shunamite, muſt cherriſh him: when as<note place="margin">Mirabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cap: de ſen.</note> 
               <hi>Senix is quaſi ſemi ſenex,</hi> an old man halfe deaths man, deſtitute of all good meanes to conuerſion, vnfit to faſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to pray, vnapt to watch, or any other exerciſe. What voice is there more lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then that of Milo, (when<note place="margin">Cicero de Sen:</note> ſeeing the young Champions ſtriuing each with other to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the conqueſt) hee cryed out with teares, <hi>At hi iam mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui ſunt,</hi> looking on his wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb facs="tcp:15058:34"/> armes, my bloode is dead; my veynes wrinckled; my ſinewes ſhrunke to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The counſell of the wiſe man may be a preſent memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to euery man, <hi>Memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Creator is tui,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle, 12</note> 
               <hi>diebus iuventutis tuae,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, while the euill dayes come not; that is, in thy proſperitie of ſtrength, in thy hopefull youth, in thy vigor and luſtines of yeeres, before forgetfull old age ouer-take thee. Take thy ſelfe vnto him, that tooke thee out of the duſt, and created thee to his owne likenes: for otherwiſe it were an euerlaſting blemiſh of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15058:34"/> ingratitude, a moſt infamous ſtampe of iniuſtice, to hope for the receit of eternall glorie, to receiue at one inſtance an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels inheritance; to enioy for nothing, a place with Chriſt; and not to tender the beſt of thy ſelfe to GOD his father. If it were pollution, to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar<note place="margin">Malac. 1, Auguſt. Serm: 36 in Luke.</note> to offer the lame and ſicke, with what face the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> canſt thou preſent that little, ſhort, and maymed peece of ſeruice, which lymping olde age will afford?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui maior est etate, maior est iniquitate,</hi> he which is the child of many yeres, no doubt is the Father of many ſinnes, for life, the longer it is, the
<pb facs="tcp:15058:35"/> more ſinfull it is. If in oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of burnt offerings, &amp; peace offerings, the young Lambes<note place="margin">Leuit. 1.</note> without blemiſh were ſelected for the ſacrifice: If the chiefe<note place="margin">Exod, 29,</note> fatte of the Ramme, made the ſweeteſt ſauour vnto the lord,<note place="margin">Leuit, 3,</note> then ſtandes it againſt the rule of decencie &amp; good manners, to ſerue in Gods meſſe, with the bare, leane, and rotten bones of ſinnes, that haue lien as many ſcore yeeres in the pit of corruption, as did Lazarus dayes in the graue. If none were admitted to ſtand before Nabuchadnezer, but children<note place="margin">Dan, 1.</note> that were moſt beautiful, how dare man ſhuffle into Gods preſence, diſioynted, crooked
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15058:35"/> old age, and ſlothfull? There is no reaſon in the world, that the world ſhould reape that harueſt, which GOD hath bought with the ſweat of his blood; no law to giue him the lees of wine, that hath taken paines to plant the vineyard, and to treade the preſſe; no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie to leaue him the glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, to whom the vvhole ſheafe belongeth; no iuſtice to deuide the heart, which hee hath made one, &amp; to giue the ſicke &amp; feeble part vnto him, and the ſtrong and luſtie vnto the deuill. <hi>Niſi venerit vobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene, 44,</note> 
               <hi>frater veſter minimus,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you bring your youngeſt brother (ſaith Ioſeph) you
<pb facs="tcp:15058:36"/> ſhall neuer ſee my face againe: So vnleſſe wee bring young Beniamine, that is, the firſt fruites of our youth, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them to our euerlaſting high Prieſt, we ſhal neuer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take his ioyfull preſence; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enioy his comfortable grace; neuer bee comforted with his diuine happines. As the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> young Samuell, &amp; young<note place="margin">1, Sam, 2 1, Reg, 18</note> Obediah, beeing (as it were) in their child clouts, miniſtred vnto the Lord: Euen ſo I, in the ſpring and prime of my youth, (no way relying vpon aged repentance) will confeſſe my ſinnes, and at the barre of Gods bountie, will I ſue out a pardon, ſaying, <hi>O God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15058:36"/> to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If in Dauids <hi>Peccaui,</hi> the fire of his deuotion did aſcend, &amp; moone the Heauens to ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd vp the wrathful ſword in the ſheath of mercie, I doubt not, but with the ſame flame to kindle the like ſacrifice; and with as ſtrong a voyce as had Eliah when he brought foode<note place="margin">1, Reg, 17</note> from Heauen, to mooue the ſame God to compaſsion. My vow ſhall be as able to quench the fire of Gods iuſtice, as was the voyce of the three chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren<note place="margin">Dan: 3,</note> that ouer-came the hote burning fornace; My voyce ſhall be as able to procure life, as was the voyce of Ezechias,<note place="margin">2, Reg, 20 Ionas, 2, 3</note> that ouercame death. As Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas
<pb facs="tcp:15058:37"/> out of the bellie of the Whale, ſo I out of the hell of ſinne, will call; As blind Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timeus for his want of ſight, ſo<note place="margin">Mar. 20,</note> I in the ſight of my wants, will cry, <hi>O GOD, bee mercifull to mee a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As young Tobias was not deſtitute of a Guide to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct<note place="margin">Tobi, 5,</note> him to Rages, ſo am not I left ignorant of the way to heauen. Abraham in his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney<note place="margin">Gene, 12,</note> to Canaan tooke a Map of the vpper Canaan, and left it regiſtred to all poſteritie: firſt therefore, <hi>Egrediendum de terra mea est,</hi> I muſt leaue my Country behind my back, <hi>de terra mea,</hi> that is, <hi>de carne mea, et de meipſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15058:37"/> and bidde adiewe to the fleſh, the world, and my ſelfe: from pride deſcending to low humilitie; leauing anger to ſhake hands with patience; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing luſt the farewell to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come chaſtitie; excluding en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to entertaine charitie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing crueltie for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of clemencie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>egrediendum est à cognatione mea,</hi> I muſt relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh &amp; forſake my own kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, that is, the old cuſtome and acquaintance I haue had with Sinne; ſhaking the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit out of doores, and beeing waſht, neuer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to my olde vomit; and beeing made whole, I will ſin
<pb facs="tcp:15058:38"/> no more.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>de domo Patris mei,</hi> I muſt turne from the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and left hand of this World; from the Prince of darkneſſe my father, to the right hand of righteouſneſſe, to the King of Kinges, my heauenly father: which dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in <hi>Terra Viuentiam,</hi> in the Land of Vertue, not in the Land of Vice; in the Land of Peace, not in the Land of Paine; in the Land of Ioy, not in the Land of Sorrowe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and be partaker of that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Benediction where-with Iſaack (in the type and figure of Chriſt, bleſſed his ſonne<note place="margin">Gene, 27</note> Iacob; <hi>Ecce ador Filij mei,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15058:38"/> the ſvveete ſmell of my Sonne: the ſweet ſmell of my Sonne, that ſauours not of the Onions and Garlicke of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, but the ſweet ſmell of my Sonne, that hath beene daintilie fedde with the choice Milke and Honnie of Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
            <p>No flight is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,<note place="margin">Iere, 51, Exod, 2.</note> then to flie out of the middle of Babilon, to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten out of Egipt: where mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries haue no period; and to trauell to the promiſed Land, where is reſt without remoue; mercie without meaſure; loue without limit; goodneſſe in all kind of greatneſſe; vvhere <hi>habitemus ſine metu, abunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
<pb facs="tcp:15058:39"/> ſine defectu, ſine fastidio epulemur:</hi> where euery Soule may (like the Done in Noabs Arke) reſt without feare, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> plentie without want, take her repaſt without contempt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>In Coelo ſola libertas.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:15058:39"/>
            <head>A prayer to be ſaid in the time of ſickneſſe.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>I Find good Lord that there are two things in mee, the one is Nature, which thou haſt framed, the other is Sin, which by mine owne follie I haue heaped: I confeſſe, O Lord, that by ſinne I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed my nature, ſo that all that is thine is extinguiſhed, and nothing left but mine owne filthines and iniquitie: Take away, good Lord, this ſinfull vaile of mire, that the pure brightnes may appeare,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:40"/> lighten mine eyes, leaſt I ſleepe in death, let not mine enemie ſay, he hath preuailed againſt mee. Enter not Lord into iudgement with mee, whether I haue deſerued this or not, for in thy ſight no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing creature ſhall be iuſtified. I ſee the paines of death due vnto me, for that the floods of iniquitie haue ouer-whelmed me; I perceiue the ſnares of mine aduerſarie ready layde, and the plagues of hell readie for my ſinnes, but thou (O Lord) art my Rocke and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, thou haſt preſerued me from the ſhell, and wilt not now forſake my groaning ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, when it hath moſt neede;
<pb facs="tcp:15058:40"/> Good Lord of thy mercy ſaue me; good Lord ſaue me, who haue loſt my ſelfe; the greater my offences are, the more is thy merites; I am thine owne good Lord, thou madeſt me, thine owne fingers faſhioned me to thine owne ſimilitude; wilt thou deface thine owne picture? wilt thou deliuer to beaſtes ſuch ſoules as confeſſe thee? No, good Lord, this is not thy nature, I wholy relie vpon thee, I truſt aſſuredly to be ſaued in the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, in his death and paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I challenge mine enemie, and defie the ſting of death; I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe his bleeding wounds, his ſtripes, his torments; his
<pb facs="tcp:15058:41"/> cruell plague, his precious death, and his bitter paſsion. I know he dyed not in vaine, but for the ſafetie of mee, and all mankind; and in this faith, hope, and knowledge, I cry to thee euen as he did, O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, into thy handes I commit my Spirit. Heare my voice, ô Lord, from thy holy temple, let my cry pierce into thine eare, receiue the ſoule of thy poore ſeruaunt, offering it ſelfe vnto thee. Not that it is worth thy preſence, beeing polluted with vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but in thy diuine power, which with one word canſt make it cleane: Cleanſe it, ô Lord I beſeech thee, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe
<pb facs="tcp:15058:41"/> it that thy holy preſence ſet thy ſeale vpon it, that mine enemie ſee it, and be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Receiue it good Lord, for to thee it yeeldeth it ſelfe, and to none other; Thou art my GOD, my Sauiour, and my Redeemer. Vnto thee be all honour, glorie, praiſe, &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, for euer.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>OEternall God and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, ſeeing that by thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie we haue quietly paſſed this night, graunt we beſeech thee, that we beſtow this day who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in thy ſeruice: ſo that all
<pb facs="tcp:15058:42"/> our thoughts, wordes and deedes, may redound to the glory of thy Name, and good example of our Bretheren. And as it hath pleaſed thee to make the ſunne to ſhine vpon the earth, to giue vs bodilie light, euen ſo vouchſafe to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate our vnderſtanding, with the brightneſſe of thy Spirit, to direct vs in the way of righteouſnes; ſo that what thing ſoeuer wee ſhall apply our ſelues vnto, our ſpeciall care and purpoſe, may be to walke in thy feare, &amp; to ſerue thee, looking for all our wealths &amp; proſperitie to come from thine onely bleſsing: &amp; that wee may take nothing in
<pb facs="tcp:15058:42"/> hand, which ſhal not be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thy moſt bleſſed will. Furthermore, that we may in ſuch ſort trauel for our bodies, and for this preſent life, that we may haue alwaies a further regard, that is, to the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie life, which thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to thy children: and in the meane ſeaſon, that it may pleaſe thee to preſerue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs both in body &amp; ſoule, to ſtrengthen vs againſt all the temptations of the deuill, and to deliuer vs from all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills, and dangers that may happen vnto vs, if wee be not defended by thy godly power. And foraſmuch as to beginne well, and not to continue is
<pb facs="tcp:15058:43"/> nothing, wee beſeech thee to receiue vs, not onely this day into thy holy protection, but alſo for the time of our whole life, continuing &amp; encreaſing in vs daily thy grace and good gifts thereof, vntill thou ſhalt bring vs to that happy eſtate, where we ſhall fully and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, be ioyned vnto thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, which is the true light of our ſoules, ſhining day and night perpetually: and to the end we may obtaine ſuch grace at thy hande, vouchſafe moſt mercifull Father, to forgiue &amp; forget all our ſinnes, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wittingly or willingly we haue committed againſt thee,
<pb facs="tcp:15058:43"/> and for thine infinite mercies ſake to pardon the ſame, as thou haſt promiſed to thoſe that aske of thee with vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hart: for whom, as for our ſelues, we make our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble petitions vnto thee, in the Name of thy ſonne, our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, in ſuch ſort as hee himſelfe hath taught vs, ſaying: Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>An Euening prayer.</head>
               <p>O Eternall God, &amp; moſt mercifull Father, who this day, and all the time of our life, haſt graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defended, nouriſhed, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb facs="tcp:15058:44"/> our ſoules and bodies, and made ſuch fatherly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for vs poore ſinners, that of thy louing kindnes we haue rich portions, not onely in the creatures of heauen and earth, but alſo in that plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redemption, which thy moſt deere ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, hath purchaſed for vs. Graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs (ô mercifull Father) the aſsiſtance of thy grace, and holy Spirit, that as our bodies ſhall nowe take their naturall reſt, euen ſo our ſoules and mindes, at the beholding of thy goodnes towards vs, may quiet themſelues in thee, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue ſuch inward pleaſure, and heauenlie ſweetnes in thy
<pb facs="tcp:15058:44"/> loue, that whatſoeuer we ſhall from henceforth either think, ſpeake, or doe, that it may be all to the honour of thy holie Name, through Ieſus Chriſt thy deere ſonne, our Lord &amp; Sauiour.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
